Hello everyone and welcome to
another lesson here at EnglishPod.
My name is Marco.
And I'm Katherine
and today we have an
elementary level lesson all
about life with a roommate.
That's right.
So sometimes during
college you have to live
with a roommate because you
know living alone is too expensive.
Also after college
I know that a lot of
people who are just
starting their jobs often
live with a roommate
to save some money.
That's right.
Or maybe your girlfriend could be considered
kind of like your romantic roommate.
I hope not.
In the sense of today's lesson we're
talking about problems with a roommate.
So let's listen to this dialogue
and we'll be back in a moment.
Charlie, do you have a second?
Yeah, what's up?
Well I went and paid the bills today
and you still haven't given me your half.
Yeah, I wanted to talk to you about that.
I agreed we would go haves on all
the bills but frankly I think it's unfair.
Unfair?
Why?
Well, you have long hair and use
the hair dryer every morning, I don't.
You leave your computer on all
night downloading torrents, I don't.
You see what I'm getting at here?
You leave the air
conditioner on day and night.
You also take 30 minutes
showers which means
you're using way more
gas and water than me.
Well, while we're on
the subject, stop bringing
your friends over for
drinks every weekend.
You always leave a mess
and keep me up all night.
Maybe you should just move
out and find another place.
Maybe you should move out.
Alright, we're back
so we have a couple of
different words that we're going to
take a look at now in language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
So the first word is a dreaded word.
That means that most people don't like it.
They fear it.
This is bills.
That's right.
You have to pay your bills.
So a bill is the paper that tells
you how much you have to pay.
That's right.
So you can have a
gas bill, an electricity
bill, a cable bill, or even at the
restaurant you ask for the bill.
Alright, so this is the amount
of money you need to pay.
And usually at the end of the month,
you receive many, many bills in the mail.
And you have to pay the companies like the
gas company and the electricity company.
That's right.
So those are bills.
Singular would be a bill.
Okay.
And so this is how the argument starts.
The two roommates decide
that they have to pay the bills,
but they don't want to split
the bills in half go halves.
They have to pay their own.
And so one person
says, listen, this isn't fair.
You leave your computer on
all night downloading torrents.
Okay.
So we understand what it
is to download something
or you download this
podcast, but a torrent.
What is that?
That's kind of technical.
That is.
So a torrent is a kind of file that
you can download from the internet.
So basically when you
want to download a
movie or some music from the internet, you
go to a website that will connect you to
someone who owns this
movie or book or music.
And they'll have a special
file that's called a torrent file.
And that's what you download.
That's right.
So it's a new way of downloading files off
the internet from many people, kind of like
a peer sharing.
That's right.
So when one person disappears or goes
offline, it shares you with another person.
That's right.
So those are torrents.
Now, well, they kept arguing
about you have to pay this.
I have to pay that.
So you said, you know what?
You should just move out.
So to move out, this is a phrase
that has two words to move out.
It means to leave this
house forever, this apartment.
So that means to find a
new place to live, right?
So I can say, oh, I'm
moving out this weekend.
That means I'm changing apartments, right?
Or my boyfriend just moved out.
Okay.
So that was really sad.
You left your house.
Okay.
So that is to move out.
And now we have a word
that is more colloquial
of how to say a
house or an apartment.
This is place.
Okay.
So let me just say a place.
So place normally is a location, okay?
Where is this place?
But we could say, hey, we're
going to have dinner at my place.
Would you like to come?
So that means we're going to
have dinner at my house, right?
My place.
This place.
Or you have a really nice place.
Thanks.
Okay.
That means you have a really nice house.
Exactly.
Okay.
So four keywords today
when we listen to the
dialogue again and
we'll be back in a little bit.
Charlie, do you have a second?
Yeah.
What's up?
Well, I went and paid the bills today
and you still haven't given me your half.
Yeah.
I wanted to talk to you about that.
I agreed we would go halves on all the
bills, but frankly, I think it's unfair.
Unfair?
Why?
Well, you have long hair and
use the hair dryer every morning.
I don't.
You leave your computer on
all night downloading torrents.
I don't.
You see what I'm getting here?
You leave the air
conditioner on day and night.
You also take 30 minute
showers, which means
you're using way more
gas and water than me.
Well, while we're on
the subject, stop bringing
your friends over for
drinks every weekend.
You always leave a mess
and keep me up all night.
Maybe you should just move
out and find another place.
Maybe you should move out.
All right, we are back
and we've got some great
phrases today coming
up in fluency builders.
Let's take a look at some
of those fluency builder.
All right.
So the first phrase that
we have, very common,
very, very common,
but also very difficult
for English learners
to answer this question.
All right.
What's up?
So if somebody says, what's
up, what does that mean?
That means what's going on?
What's new?
How are you?
How is it going?
Okay.
Hi.
So how should you answer this?
Okay.
So think of what's up is being a question
about what's new, what's happening.
You can say, what's up?
Oh, not much.
Not much.
Okay.
What's up means?
What's new?
Oh, not much is new.
Not much.
Everything is the same.
Okay.
Hey.
Hi.
How are you?
It's another way to say hi.
Okay.
But you can't say this guy.
Right.
Or sometimes English
learners will say, fine,
thank you, because they
think that what's up means?
How are you?
No, that's different.
So you cannot say, fine, thank you, fine.
Well, these are words about how
that answer, how are you questions?
Mm-hmm.
But this isn't how are you questions.
Right.
This is a, what's new question?
Yeah.
Hi.
Okay.
So somebody says, what's up?
You can say not much or
you can say, hey, what's up?
You can say, what's up back?
What's up?
What's up with you?
Yeah.
Okay.
So that's our first phrase.
Now when the guy
was talking about the
hairdryer and the
computer, he finished off that
paragraph by saying, you
see what I'm getting at here?
Okay.
You're doing this.
You use the hairdryer.
Leave the computer on.
Do you see what I'm getting at here?
What's phrase, do you
see what I'm getting at?
It means, do you understand
what I'm talking about?
Do you see my point?
That means I haven't
said exactly what I mean,
but you should
understand what I'm saying.
So he's saying you're wasting electricity.
You use all of these
services more than I do.
Right.
And we could say, maybe Marco didn't get a
good grant in his English chest last week.
I say, listen, maybe
it has to do with your
study habits or how much you love video
games or how little time you spend at school.
Do you see what I'm getting at?
Okay.
So you're not saying
directly that I don't study.
You're just telling me the reasons
maybe why as to who I'm not studying.
Right.
Like a hint.
Okay.
So that's what you say when you don't
tell somebody directly what the problem is.
You say, you see what I'm getting at here?
Do you see what I'm getting at?
Okay.
Getting at means hinting.
Mm-hmm.
Okay.
And our last phrase, when they kept talking
about the bills, one of the persons said,
you are using way more
gas and water than me.
So what about this way more
way more way means much or a lot?
So we could say, you
are using a lot more
water than I am or you're
using way more water.
Okay.
This is very spoken language.
This is not written language.
So don't write this down on your tests, but
a way more means a lot more much more.
Okay.
You can say, Bob is way
more attractive than Bill.
That's right.
This is way more
interesting than that show.
Okay.
So you can say way more
instead of much more
or a lot more, but it's
usually spoken English.
Exactly.
All right.
Let's listen to our
dialogue for the last time.
And we'll be back in a
bit to talk a little bit more.
Charlie.
Do you have a second?
Yeah.
What's up?
Well, I went and paid the bills today
and you still haven't given me your half.
Yeah, I wanted to talk to you about that.
I agreed we would go haves on all the
bills, but frankly, I think it's unfair.
Unfair?
Why?
Well, you have long hair and
use the hair dryer every morning.
I don't.
You leave your computer on
all night downloading torrents.
I don't.
You see what I'm getting here?
You leave the air
conditioner on day and night.
You also take 30 minute
showers, which means
you're using way more
gas and water than me.
Well, while we're on the
subject, stop bringing your friends.
Oh, we're for drinks every weekend.
You always leave a mess
and keep me up all night.
Maybe you should just move
out and find another place.
Maybe you should move out.
San Marco, have you ever had any
of these problems with a roommate?
I've actually stayed away from
roommates because of issues like this.
You mean you have not had many roommates
because you're afraid of this situation?
Yeah, I've always actually tried to live on
my own by myself, like in a small apartment
or studio, or if I have to have a roommate,
maybe just like one, not like a house full
of roommates because
I think the more people
there are, the little bit
more complicated it gets.
And if it's just two, you
know, it's a little bit simpler.
This is true, although
sometimes I think it depends
on the people that you're
sharing a house with.
I've had one awkward experience
where people did not want to pay ever.
Really?
Because late with
our payments and one
situation where people
were very good about it.
So always remembered and very helpful.
So it really depends.
Yeah.
I think it's hard to live
with someone always,
of course, even,
you know, if you start
living with your girlfriend or boyfriend or
you get married, it's kind of different to
live with someone,
you know, and especially
money-wise, I think it always
complicates things with people.
Definitely.
So I think you're right, though.
If there's two people, it's
very easy to share the bills.
But if there's five
people or six people, it's
very hard to find out who spent
more money or what the rules are.
Yeah.
So it can get a little
bit complicated, but
I'm sure a lot of our
listeners have probably
had roommates before, maybe
in college, maybe even now.
So let's hear those
experiences and maybe
those good and bad stories
about living with other people.
So please get in touch with us.
Our website is EnglishPod.com.
There's lots of
places for you to ask
questions and to post your
own experiences with roommates.
We hope to see you there.
And until next time, bye, everyone.